Inventory of the Hugh Baker Cox papers, 1917-1973
University of Wyoming. American Heritage Center.
Hugh Baker Cox papers
1917-1973
Cox, Hugh Baker, 1905-1973
03128
1.45 cubic ft. (2 boxes)
University of Wyoming. American Heritage Center.
Hugh Baker Cox was an antitrust lawyer who worked for the U.S. Department of Justice. The collection contains correspondence, memoranda, legal opinions, and other materials related to Cox's work
Biography of Hugh Baker Cox
Hugh Baker Cox (1905-1973) was born in Logan, Iowa and grew up in Lincoln, Nebraska. He earned a bachelor of arts degree at the University of Nebraska in 1926 and became a Rhodes Scholar the same year. He then received a bachelor's degree in English from Christ Church at Oxford in 1929 followed by a law degree in 1930 under the Vinerian scholarship. Cox was admitted to the New York State Bar in 1933 and in 1935 he joined the antitrust division of the U.S. Department of Justice. He was counsel for the Department before the Temporary National Economic Committee from 1938-1939. In 1942, he was assigned to the Board of Economic Warfare, working in London on economic intelligence activities. He was named assistant attorney general in 1943 in charge of the War Division and from 1943-1945 was assistant solicitor general. In 1944, he was directly involved in formulation of federal policy regarding a dispute between Montgomery Ward and the National War Labor Board which resulted in the seizure of the company under presidential executive order. Cox returned to private legal practice in Washington, D.C. in 1945.
Scope and Content
Collection contains subject files and contents from five binders of correspondence, memoranda, legal opinions, reports, press releases, and printed materials related to Cox's work with the Department of Justice.
Access Restrictions
There are no access restrictions on the materials for research purposes, and the collection is open to the public.
Related Materials
There are no known other archival collections created by Hugh Baker Cox at the date of processing.
Acquisition Information
This material was received from Mr. and Mrs. Hugh Cox in 1962 and 1974.
Access Terms
Montgomery Ward.; United States. Dept. of Justice. Antitrust Division.; World War, 1939-1945 -- Economic aspects.; Antitrust law -- United States.; Alien property.; War and emergency powers -- United States.; Lawyers.
Politics, Government, and Law; Laws and Legislation; Civil Procedure and Courts; Business, Industry, Labor, and Commerce
Container List
- Alien Property Custodian, 1943 (Box 1)
- Amazon Rubber, undated (Box 1)
- Antitrust - Foreign Contracts Act, 1943 (Box 1)
- Antitrust Matters - General, 1943-1944 (Box 1)
- Antitrust - Price Agreements (Basing Point), 1945 (Box 1)
- Aviation, 1945 (Box 1)
- Charters, circa 1940-1941 (Box 1)
- Corrupt Practices Act, 1938, 1944 (Box 1)
- Employment - Government & Private, 1943-1945 (Box 1)
- Executive Orders - Seizures, 1936-1944 (Box 1)
- Foreign Agents Registration Act, 1942 (Box 1)
- Legal Memoranda, 1943-1945 (Box 1)
- Montgomery Ward & Co., Incorporated, 1943-1944 (Box 1)
- Miscellaneous items, undated (Box 1)
- O'Mahoney file, 1943-1944 (Box 1)
- Opinions - Attorney General, 1941-1945 (Box 1)
- State Taxes during Federal Operation, 1945 (Box 1)
- Obituaries, 1973 (Box 1)
- Agricultural Adjustment Act, circa 1937 (Box 2)
- Agricultural legislation in relation to antitrust investigation of the food industries, undated (Box 2)
- Aluminum Co. of America memo, 1936 November 24 (Box 2)
- American Optical Co. Atty.-Client Priv. Brief, 1941 (Box 2)
- Antitrust Decree Conviction for Contempt, 1937 July 28 (Box 2)
- Cases of major importance (since 1900), 1938 December 16 (Box 2)
- Notes prepared for Mr. Arnold, undated (Box 2)
- Price reductions memo, 1940 November 15 (Box 2)
- Violations by Labor, 1940 March 19 (Box 2)
- Appealability, 1940 March 15 (Box 2)
- Cartelisation articles, circa 1935-1938 (Box 2)
- Robert C. Barnard memos, bibliography, bid depositories, circa 1941 (Box 2)
- Bill of Particulars, 1921, 1939, undated (Box 2)
- Copper-Volstead Act, 1938 (Box 2)
- Certiorari, 1939 (Box 2)
- Civil liberties, 1939 (Box 2)
- Consent Decree in Treble Damage Action, 1938 November 29 (Box 2)
- Constitutional Limitations on the Powers of the States, 1936 May 26 (Box 2)
- Contempt proceedings, undated (Box 2)
- Convict Labor cases, 1935 October 17 (Box 2)
- Cooper v. U.S. Argument in CCA & The Argument, circa 1938 (Box 2)
- McDowell & Stemmler memos, 1940 May (Box 2)
- Judge Coxe Opinion - Mandel v. Cooper Corp., 1941 December 9 (Box 2)
- Cranberry memo, Criminal Appeals Act, Darby Lumber Co. Recommendation, Limits of Reviewability, Demurrer, Elizabethan Patents of Monopoly, Evidence, Questions arising in Antitrust cases, 1938-1941 (Box 2)
- FTC Act, 1936, 1938 (Box 2)
- Monopoly & competition in steel, 1939 March 7 (Box 2)
- Hartford Empire - Plaintiff's memo, 1941 March 6 (Box 2)
- Hepburn Act & Hinderlider memo, 1937-1938 (Box 2)
- Housing - Certain Lands memo, Debentures memo, Eminent domain memo (Bird), 1935 (Box 2)
- Eminent domain memo (Kimble), Finnegan v. Soevig memo, McLean letter, 1935-1936 (Box 2)
- Oil, 1941 (Box 2)
- Opinion, Owlett memo, Paper Bag Program, 1917-1938 (Box 2)
- Pipe Line Regulations, Pleas of Nolo, Privileged Communications, 1940 (Box 2)
- Proposed legislation, Robinson Patman Act, Rule of Reason, 1936-1938 (Box 2)
- St. Joseph memo, Standard Oil Co. of Indiana, Stammler memo on State & Municipal statutes & ordinances, State inspection laws, 1936-1939 (Box 2)
- Subpoena, Supreme Court, Taylor Act memo, Tax Power, TNEC, Tin Can Invest., Venue, 1935-1940 (Box 2)
- Immunity to arrest in PA, Indictment, Interstate Commerce Commission, Jurisdiction of State to adjudicate Constitutional Act of Congress, 1936-1941 (Box 2)
- Jurisdictional Strike, Lanza, U.S. v. Masonite, McLean estate memo, 1936-1941 (Box 2)
- Master's power to hold hearings, etc; McGovern memo on Fraud under Crim. Code; Morgan v. U.S.; U.S. v. National Retail Lumber Dealers; Newspaper industry; Norris - La Guardia Act, 1937-1942 (Box 2)